WWW.MY-SUBS.CO
- Shall I help?
- Well, you can.
- You know what these
are, don't you? - No.
Pig boards. They control the pigs.
Are you annoyed we've given
Yew Tree Farm to Mr Mason?
I'm annoyed you fixed it
while I was in London,
but no, he's a good man.
And I hear pigs are his speciality.
No wonder you were convinced.
So now that you've settled in, have you
decided what your next task will be?
You haven't done much about the repair shop
while I was away, so I'll start with that.
I had an idea to put it on the edge of
the estate with access to the village.
For passing trade?
Why not?
Is Papa ready for that?
Hmm. You must be gentle with him.
When does Mr Mason move in?
His equipment's already there.
And the Drewes leave on Wednesday,
so there's no point in waiting.
And what about his old farm?
Mr Henderson's taken over the land.
He's going to move his uncle into
the house, much good may it do him.
Nay. There's no need for bitterness now.
Things have worked out well.
- You're right.
- Oh, I tell you what.
Why don't we go over on the day? We'll
take a picnic tea and lend him a hand.
I could come, too. Another pair of hands.
And very welcome, I have no doubt.
Good news?
Oh, it's just a friend who's
going to be in London.
- He wants to meet up.
- He?
It's nothing like that.
It's Bertie Pelham, the
agent from Brancaster Castle.
I remember him. He shot with us.
And he helped get the magazine
out during my night of terror.
The Dowager Countess.
Hello, Granny. What are you doing here?
My dear. I am in need of a favour.
Is Cora about?
Er, no, she's got some
charity thing in the village.
Oh, good.
Why don't I like the sound of that?
I'll leave you.
The Minister of Health
is paying us a visit.
Mr Chamberlain? I don't think so.
Now, listen. He's on an
inspection tour of the north.
He wants to see what's been
happening since the war.
- Seems very sensible.
- And I want him to come here.
I want him to listen to our arguments
against the York Hospital's plans.
Mama, what is the point?
Don't be jejune. You know very well,
one word from Westminster and
the scheme would be abandoned.
But why would he say the word, and
why would he ever come to Downton?
You know, Neville Chamberlain's
wife was born Anne de Vere Cole.
Guess who was her godfather.
You guess for me.
Your late papa, the
sixth Earl of Grantham.
He and her father served in the
Crimea together when they were young.
I have known her since she was born.
I admit I am quite interested, but
when it comes to getting him here,
I would say you have no more chance
than a cat in hell without claws.
We'll see.
Mr Carson has suggested we might
have dinner in our cottage tonight,
so I thought I'd ask your advice.
Oh, is this going to be a regular thing?
I don't think so. Once in a while.
Well, there's pate left
over and some chops.
- I'll make up a basket.
- Would you?
Oh, that would be so kind.
When did you last cook?
I've done the odd thing...
Oh, well, of course, as we
all know, anyone can cook.
Don't be like that. It's not my idea.
But it might be nice.
Mrs Patmore's just jealous.
I'm sure she's not.
But I would be grateful for the basket.
Well, maybe I am.
I nearly forgot. That chap, Henry...
- Talbot?
- Exactly.
Yes, he telephoned while you were out.
He's going to be in Yorkshire on Wednesday
to look at a car and he wants
you to watch him doing it.
Hmm. To watch him looking at a car?
Well, not quite. He's driving
it round some track nearby.
- At Catterick.
- Testing it.
Seeing how it handles.
- I could take you, if you like.
- Would you?
Well, I'd like to see it.
- How about you?
- I'll be in London on Wednesday.
Edith has a date.
- No, I don't.
- Of course not.
What do you mean, "Of course not"?
Doctor Clarkson seems to be coming round.
Isobel's bringing him for a
drink tonight with Dickie Merton.
So that's why Mama paid her visit.
When? What did she want?
Neville Chamberlain is coming north.
She wants him to dine here, so she
can convince him to support her.
If he's on a tour, it'll be far
too late to alter his schedule.
That's what I said, but she seems
to think she can persuade him.
Is it wrong to hope she's mistaken?
Anything interesting?
It's Sergeant Willis saying he'll collect
me on Wednesday at nine, to go to York.
For the trial.
Would you like me to come, too?
- Could you get the time off?
- Well, I could ask.
You shouldn't have to
go to the trial alone.
What trial?
Miss Baxter has been called
to be a witness on Wednesday.
I want to go along, keep her company.
- I think you should.
- Mr Carson will understand.
I'm only a character witness.
Character witnesses can
make all the difference.
Why do they want you to testify?
There's a man being
tried for theft and I...
I knew him once.
Will your words affect the outcome?
- Possibly.
- You must think about it carefully.
She has thought about it,
Mr Bates. Very carefully.
- Where were you?
- Oh, I'm sorry, Mr Barrow.
It was only coffee for the family,
so I thought Andy could manage.
He could. But it's for me to say, not you.
I'm going into the village in
a while. Do you want to come?
Thanks, but no, thanks.
I thought you needed some things.
Nothing urgent.
Right. Is that it?
Er... Yes.
I'm glad to see you here again, Dickie.
Well, it's very good to be here, but
it's only about the row, I'm afraid.
Oh, never mind that.
We've brought Doctor Clarkson with
us because there's something that you,
or at any rate, Cora, will want to hear.
Do I detect that you're changing sides?
Er, maybe.
Have you told my mother?
Poor man. If he's changing his
mind, don't let's put him off.
Oh, that reminds me. I
have a message from her.
She says that the Health Minister
is happy to dine here this Friday.
What? How did she manage that?
She must have found a
way to blackmail him.
- You don't mean that.
- I wouldn't put it past her.
If she's convinced him to come here,
she can make him condemn the scheme.
Well, she mustn't.
And I want the three of
you here to support me.
Aye, aye, Captain.
Is Mr Barrow getting on your nerves?
- Only earlier, you seemed to --
- No, it's not that.
He only means to be friendly.
I know. And he was good to
me when I first arrived.
So, what is it, then?
Well...
Since I've come, I've got to
know a bit more about him.
I don't like to say with a lady present.
We both know Mr Barrow pretty well.
The point is, I wouldn't want
to give him any wrong ideas.
I'm not sure that's fair.
Fair or not, I think it's
better if he knows what's what.
I bear him no ill will, mind.
We are what we are.
Isn't that the truth?
My compliments to the chef.
Who is Mrs Patmore, not me.
What was Mr Molesley asking?
Er, he wants to accompany Miss
Baxter into York on Wednesday morning.
Apparently, you've said she can go.
I have, yes.
- Will you let him?
- I don't see why not.
- What's it for?
- Sergeant Willis needs her help.
Sergeant Willis again?
Do other butlers have to contend with
the police arriving every ten minutes?
Not often.
Now, are you ready?
Hmm.
Are... Are these done enough?
Yes.
Shall I fetch the vegetables?
This plate's cold, which is a pity.
Ah, what's this?
What do you think?
Bubble and squeak.
As a vegetable with lamb?
I like it with lamb.
Well, we mustn't let it get cold.
This knife could do with sharpening.
All settled in for the night?
She is, but she won't sleep a wink.
She's too annoyed and I don't blame her.
- What's happened now?
- She says Doctor Clarkson has only planned
to throw her over for Mrs Crawley.
- She's seen it coming.
- What do you mean?
He doesn't want to support
her ladyship any more.
What cheek!
Don't go working yourself up.
Who does he think he is?
Jumped up little saw-bones!
I should steer clear.
No doubt.
But you and I don't think
alike, do we, Mr Spratt?
On this or any other subject.
I'll wish you good night.
When's your train?
- Nine. - Is this
another magazine crisis?
No. But I am interviewing
possible editors.
Women?
- Women. - Well, I approve.
Good luck with that.
- But then, who's the date with?
- It's not a date.
It's just a friend, as I keep saying.
What are you up to today? Haven't
you got some plan with a racing car?
Later. We're looking for a site
for the repair shop this morning.
Then we'll go over to
Catterick after lunch.
I want to look in on Mason before we do.
- He's moving in today.
- As long as the pigs are settled.
You joke, but I am concerned.
I've asked him to take over, but
pig-keeping needs physical strength,
- now I think of it.
- You're right, of course.
They're strong and can be dangerous.
Ask him if he's up to it.
- I think I must.
- A day of racing cars and pigs.
Who could better that?
- Who's dining at home this time?
- Nobody.
It's to welcome Daisy's Mr Mason.
He's moving in today.
Wish him well from me.
And I hope he gets more fun out
of his hamper than Mr Carson did.
Why? What was the matter with it?
Nothing was the matter with it.
Except for the fact that, I don't
seem to cook like his mother.
Oh, I think the correct response
is to say "Men!" and sigh.
What's this?
Don't mind us.
- How can I help?
- Miss Baxter is expecting me?
Daisy, run and fetch her.
Look after Miss Baxter, Sergeant.
- She's in a very frail frame of mind.
- I'll do me best.
But we're after catching a nasty fish
and he's bound to thresh about a bit.
And we'll get caught in the spray?
Good luck, love.
If we put the gate here, you'd be on
a lane that links with the main road.
You'd get power and plumbing
from the supply at King's Barrow.
Why don't we put the repair shed there?
King's Barrow is a working farm.
There isn't a spare farmyard
half as accessible as here.
We ought to look at the costs.
It's good of you to come with me today.
Glad to, but he won't want me there.
Nonsense. You have far more
in common with him than I do.
Is it serious?
He's attractive and nice,
and it's good to remember
I'm a youngish woman again.
But that's all.
Youngish?
I don't mean to sound snobbish,
but I won't marry down.
Was Mr Matthew Crawley so
very special in that way?
Matthew was the heir to
the earldom and estate.
I don't want to be
grander than my husband.
Or richer.
It may surprise you, but I agree
it's important to be balanced,
that one should not be far
stronger than the other.
I just don't think it has much
to do with money or position.
Is that how you felt about Sybil?
To all of you, she had
everything and I had nothing.
She was the great lady, and
I the man who drove the cars,
but that wasn't true for us.
We were evenly matched, Sybil and I.
She was strong in her beliefs, so was I.
We were a marriage of
equals. We were very happy.
I think we see that now.
The family, I mean.
Not at first, you're right.
But now.
- Good day to you.
- Good day?
A wonder you've got the
nerve to speak to me.
- I beg your pardon?
- Throwing over my lady,
when she's been running this
village since you were eating
porridge in the glen with your mummy.
I don't believe I am required
to justify my actions to you.
Because you can't.
Tell me, what would you
call it? Gratitude?
Because I'd call it treason.
Would you? Well, I call it impertinence,
to a degree that is not acceptable.
And I'm afraid you haven't
heard the last of this.
Well, you look very chirpy.
Oh, I think we'll have fun.
Besides, I've had some news.
They've nearly finished
the work on my house.
- Oh, that was quick.
- Was it?
It doesn't feel very
quick, but it's almost done.
Now you just have to find some customers.
But it's exciting, isn't it?
- Did you hear?
- That he changed his plea? Yes.
I was in court. I've only just come out.
I expect when he heard that you turned
up, he must've known it was pointless.
So I've been spared.
How do you feel?
In one way, I feel relieved, of course.
The newspapers won't find me and
there'll be no repercussions.
- But?
- I suppose I'd worked myself up
into facing him across courtroom,
this man who ruined my life,
and now it feels a bit anticlimactic.
Shall I go back in and ask him
to plead not guilty after all?
No, thank you.
We should leave. Sergeant
Willis is fetching the car.
It does me good to see a friendly
woman bustling about a kitchen.
I've got tea for all of us,
and a snack for you later on.
You're an angel of mercy.
Are we interrupting?
Not a bit of it, m'lady.
You're very welcome here.
We had just wanted to look
in to see how you were doing.
Daisy can tell you where
to find our office.
Daisy will be a great help to me.
We wanted to discuss the pigs.
- Shall we go outside?
- We can talk here, m'lady.
There's nothing private about it.
Very well.
Of course, I understand you
have a lot of experience.
A great deal.
I'm top at pigs.
But Lady Mary is a little worried
about the physical side of it.
Prising a boar off a sow or taking
the piglets from their mother.
Is this because I'm older than I was?
Of course, you may have already
chosen a farm hand to help you.
We've discussed it, Mr Mason and I.
He'll give me warning when there's
any chance of a bit of strong arm
and I'll walk down from the house.
So you'll be there for the servicing,
and the separating and the rest of it?
We'll plan it round when
Mr Carson can release me.
- It's not every day.
- That's very good of you, Andrew.
I want to train in the
care of pigs, m'lady.
I want to learn as much
as I can about farming.
Oh, I see. Well, good.
That seems to settle it.
We must go. We're on our way
to Catterick and we're late.
- We hope you'll be very happy here.
- Thank you.
Well, I do want to train.
I do want to learn.
It were no word of a lie.
Why does Lord Hexham spend
so much time in Tangier?
I suppose he likes it there.
If I had Brancaster Castle, I'm
not sure I'd ever want to leave.
I agree.
He's not really a country type.
More arty than sporty,
if you know what I mean.
He doesn't hunt or shoot?
Hardly. He paints.
What does he paint?
The young men of Tangier, mainly.
You know, scenes of local life.
And he's never wanted to marry?
I wouldn't quite say that.
It's always been sort of
understood that he and his cousin,
Adela Graham, will marry eventually.
Understood by whom?
By the two sets of parents.
How romantic.
But you like him?
You wouldn't ever want to
find something else to do?
I'd hate to leave Brancaster
and I'm very fond of Cousin Peter,
even if he isn't a countryman.
He hasn't a nasty bone in his body.
What are we doing this evening?
Have I got your evening, too?
Come to my flat for a
drink, I'll show it to you.
Then we can go somewhere else. You choose.
What a racy plan.
Not as racy as all that, worse luck.
But I'd like your opinion.
And you shall have it.
Charlie's going to beat him
again. It infuriates him.
Mr Rogers is a good driver.
I know, but they take such risks.
I hate it. I just hate it.
There's no such thing
as slow motor racing.
Even so.
And there's no such thing as safe love.
Real love means giving
someone the power to hurt you.
Which I won't concede easily.
She went well.
She's perfect, Charles.
Don't change a thing.
I think I started after you.
You're a bad loser!
- Well?
- How fast.
That is the general idea.
It looks like she handles well.
Will you take her to Brooklands?
Brooklands and other tracks.
I think I've found my new
car. What do you say, Charlie?
Well, she must be good to beat me.
- If you did.
- Oh, I did and I will again.
Then we must celebrate.
Well, there's a pub at Catterick.
Not for me, I'm afraid. I have to go home.
- Oh.
- Let's go anyway.
Okay. Just let me get changed.
Help him to enjoy it.
You don't have to marry him, but you
do have to let him enjoy this moment.
You're not nervous? Because I would be.
No. I'm looking forward to it.
We'll make a pig man of you yet.
I'll lend you some books
when we go inside.
- Books?
- On pig breeding and care.
You need to know the theory of it.
You'll be glad of the knowledge.
It makes the work more logical.
Well, then.
Thank you, we'll be in touch.
- How many more?
- Just one.
Miss Edmunds.
Send her in.
If you'd like to go in now.
Please sit down.
I've been reading about
your many achievements.
Oh, I see you were born in '92.
I know I might seem too young to be
an editor, but I do have experience.
I was just going to say
we're born in the same year.
Er, have you seen a copy
of our latest edition?
I produced it, actually.
Our editor had left, so it was down
to me and the rest of the office,
and during one horror-filled
night, we did it.
But then are you sure you need me?
Oh, I am. But I have at least proved
you're old enough to be an editor.
Because I was.
1892 seems a million years ago now.
Another time, another age.
That might be worth exploring.
Victorian babies grown into modern women.
And the price they've paid.
Oh. Thank you, Audrey.
Mmm, this is something like it.
I think you'll do well here.
So do I.
And you know what I wish?
That our Daisy would live here.
You can still work at the big
house, but make a home with me.
- I don't know.
- What is it?
A 20-minute walk? What's that?
I'll have to think about it.
I wouldn't have to think long.
This place is like heaven to me.
You never set foot off a
pavement for 18 years,
and now it's all harvests and pig farming.
Well, not everyone's right
for what they're born to.
Very true. These are the books I spoke of.
You'll learn most from the work, I know,
but, er, they'll give you a grounding.
- If you're serious.
- I am.
Now, what else can I give you?
Another cup of tea, why not?
Don't mind if I do.
I'm afraid Mummy, and Daddy,
and Aunt Edith are all away,
so you must make do with Granny and Donk.
Is Granny Violet a Red Indian?
Why on earth do you say that?
Nanny said she was on the war path.
Come and look at these
books I've put out for you.
These are some of the places
Donk and I have visited.
Chamberlain's office rang to confirm
that he is dining here on Friday.
I wish he weren't.
But you'll line up the opposition?
Certainly. I already have.
What a nuisance it is.
Mama is not a good loser.
She's had so little experience.
You couldn't just back off and
let the cards fall as they may.
Robert, for 30 years, I've striven
to let your mother have her own way
but this is too important.
I appreciate that her
motives are honourable,
but that's not enough when
she's damaging people's lives.
Oh.
We can cancel, if I'm
allowed to say you're ill.
I'm not ill enough, and
she'd only rearrange it.
She can obviously get Chamberlain
to do whatever she wants,
though heaven knows why.
What's this?
That's the Sphinx, darling. In Egypt.
- What?
- The Sphinx.
A creature of secrets
that she never reveals.
Rather like Granny Violet.
What time will you get there, on Friday?
Well, not much before eight.
I want to be in possession of the room
by the time Mr Chamberlain arrives.
Oh, dear!
Bad news?
Oh, dear...
I wouldn't have brought it if I'd known.
Er, Spratt, would you ask
Denker to come up here please?
Of course, m'lady.
You're quite agitated.
Denker has disgraced herself.
Well, how distressing for you.
It's not that so much.
It means I shall have to find a new maid.
Yes, I see. A real punishment.
M'lady?
Is it true you called
Doctor Clarkson a traitor?
What? Surely not? Denker?
I just thought he'd behaved
very badly towards your ladyship.
It is not your place even to
have opinions of my acquaintance.
Let alone express them.
He can't claim your friendship now?
Not when he's turned against you!
If I withdrew my friendship from
everyone who had spoken ill of me,
my address book would be empty.
Yes, but surely...
For a lady's maid to insult a
physician in the open street!
You've read too many novels, Denker.
You've seen too many moving pictures.
I was sticking up for you.
And for that, I will
write a tepid character,
which may enable you to
find employment elsewhere.
But from this house,
you must go, forthwith.
But m'lady...
You may stay tonight, but
you must go tomorrow.
Go!
Are you sure? I can't believe Doctor
Clarkson could wish her to lose her position.
Then he shouldn't have sent it.
When we unleash the dogs of war,
we must go where they take us.
Sorry about that. There
was rather a queue.
It's popular. That's a good sign.
Oh, you don't know the place?
You'll laugh at me, but I've
hardly ever been in a public house.
Matthew wasn't really a pub man and
Papa goes into the Grantham Arms
about once a year to have
a drink with the tenants.
Well, I'm afraid my life is
an altogether rougher affair.
Consider me warned.
So the car's a success?
Well, I wasn't convinced
it would be, but it is.
You must have a go sometime.
I hope that's a real offer.
You know, I didn't realise
you were so keen, Tom. Blast!
You could have driven her today.
You know I came to Downton as a chauffeur?
Oh, Mary told me.
But then, not every chauffeur
has a real love of cars.
That's true enough.
Oh, I'll tell you who was
talking about you the other day.
Evelyn Napier.
- Oh, how is he?
- He's well.
Still single, of course, and, I
suspect, still pining for you.
He will pine in vain, but
I'm very fond of him.
La Belle Dame sans Merci.
What does that mean?
It means Lady Mary knows what she's about.
Tell you what, next time you're down
south, why don't we all have dinner?
I'd love that.
- You are funny.
- What do you mean?
The way you have to keep making
reasons for why you'll meet.
You to watch him drive cars, you
to have dinner with a friend.
Why can't you just say, "I'd
love to spend more time with you,
"when can we do it?"
You see? He may have
assimilated in some ways,
but he still fights playing by the rules.
What are those?
Oh! I didn't hear you come in.
Mr Mason's lent me some books on
pig-rearing and farming, generally.
I'm going to help with the pigs.
Oh, I see.
Which will you start with?
The red one, I think.
The "red one." Who's it by?
FJ Connell.
Does that mean anything to you?
Not a lot.
This must be the most sophisticated
room I've ever been in.
The taste is all Michael's.
He was very artistic and very clever.
So, are you going to live here?
I think I'll live here more.
I'd like a life away from Downton.
Because you like London?
Well, the house, the estate,
they're all Mary's now,
more than Papa realises.
It's time for me to strike
out in my own direction,
not just dawdle in Mary's wake.
When do you go home this time?
Tomorrow. My work is done here.
I've found my new editor and
we've got a government minister
coming for dinner on Friday,
so we're all on parade.
That's very swanky.
- Is your father political?
- Not at all.
It's my grandmother who's invited him.
How impressive!
She is rather.
Shall we go?
I love the Cafe de Paris.
How did you know to choose it?
I knew we'd love the same things.
God, what a relief.
I thought I might be pushing my luck.
Oh, no.
I suppose you've guessed
how much I like you.
You don't know me.
I know you enough to think about
you all the time when we're apart.
That's very sweet.
Of course, I haven't much to offer.
You have a great deal to offer
and I am not sure I'm worthy of it,
but for now let's just enjoy a good dinner
and some dancing.
No arguments here.
- So it was a good day?
- Oh, yes.
A happy ending to a trying
time for the poor man.
Daisy fought well in his cause.
If not always very sensibly.
He's a lovely chap, though,
kind and considerate.
Oh, he wants Daisy to live there,
but I suppose that's understandable.
He must be lonely.
He's not lonely. He's
lived on his own for years.
- He's used to it.
- He enjoyed a bit of company today.
He was just being polite.
I expect he was longing for us to go.
You mustn't mind when Mr Mason
makes new friends, Daisy,
now that he's here among us.
Of course I don't mind.
I just think he's fine as he is.
I'm ready to walk up to
the cottage if you are.
- Of course. - Ah, Mrs
Patmore, I haven't thanked you
for our supper the other night.
I'm always happy to help.
I'm very grateful.
But another time, I wonder if you might go
through the cooking of it with Mrs Hughes.
- Oh, yes? - It's been a
while since she's played
with her patty pans, and she's
got some catching-up to do.
You'd be glad of the help, wouldn't you?
Very glad and very grateful.
And now I must fetch my coat.
I'm sorry, Miss Denker.
I simply don't see I have a role to play.
So you're just going to sit
there and let me be dismissed?
How did it happen?
- Were you drunk?
- No, I was not drunk!
I was shocked!
Shocked at the short memory of a
doctor who's failed his patroness!
I doubt he sees it in that light.
That's the way I saw it
and I acted accordingly.
Am I to blame if I have
a very passionate nature?
Any more of that talk and
I won't be able to sleep.
You won't sleep a wink if I am
still sacked when we go upstairs.
That's a risk I'll have to take.
♪ Crying cockles and
mussels Alive, alive, oh ♪
I'm dreading this dinner on Friday.
So are we all, but we
have to get through it.
I'm afraid Mama seems to see this argument as
the last battle, the last big fight of her life.
If she loses, there'll be hell to pay.
Then there'll be hell to pay.
Added to which, I'm feeling pretty rough.
I'm sure it's only indigestion,
but whether it is or not,
I'll be glad of a chance
to put my feet up.
It's too late to cancel, but I'd be
happy to manage the evening without you,
if you're really ill.
Mama would only say I'd ratted on her.
No. As you say, I'll get through it
and then take things
quietly for a few days.
How did that happen?
I threw a book and it caught it.
Oh, yes. The red one.
Why did you throw it?
Why did you throw the book, Andy?
- You can't read, can you?
- No. I can't bloody read!
Go on! Have a good laugh about it!
I'm not laughing.
You've been good at hiding
it. I must say that.
Flicking through your magazines.
I only look at the pictures.
Why did you not learn at school?
I fooled around until it was too late.
I learned how to sign my name,
which was all I needed in service.
But now you want to be a farmer.
I could be a farm labourer,
but I want more than that.
And if I can't read, then
it won't be possible.
So another dream goes west.
It doesn't have to.
I'll teach you to read and
write, too, if you want.
I must be too stupid.
I've never picked it up so far, and
I would have if I had half a brain.
That's not true. You're a clever lad.
You will get the hang of it. Trust me.
- But what would the others say?
- We won't tell them.
We'll talk about it in
the morning, all right?
Mr Barrow.
I've not behaved well towards you.
And I'm sorry for it.
I've known worse.
Good night, Andy.
Oh! You're up early.
I suppose you have quite a day ahead.
- Are you packed?
- No.
I have not packed.
Shouldn't leave it too long.
You should take up her
breakfast and dress her,
to be sure of your reference,
and then, er, head off.
Is that all you've got to say?
Don't look at me. It's not my fault
and there is nothing I can do.
Did they catch your nephew?
- What?
- Your nephew.
The one who was on the
run from the police.
The one you sheltered here.
Did they catch him?
I don't believe so. No.
I wonder if that was because
he was allowed to rest here.
I think, maybe, it was.
Septimus Spratt, if I am sacked,
I am taking you down with me.
And my sin is not a criminal offence.
What can I do?
I can't talk to her before she's dressed.
No. Well, while you're waiting, you
can think of what you're going to say.
Unless you want to find
yourself sewing mail bags.
I'm not promising anything. I mean,
suppose she doesn't listen to me?
You'd better hope she does, Mr Spratt.
You'd better hope she does.
I think she likes him, yes. But
I don't believe she's serious.
Why not?
Lady Mary has quite a
sense of her own importance
and I doubt he's enough for her.
Besides, what would he do here?
Hang about, testing his cars on the drive?
He could always get a job.
Doing what?
I'm not convinced there's a big
demand for racing drivers in Thirsk.
So, Lady Mary does not believe
that love conquers all?
We mustn't be hard on
her. She is what she is.
But I'd say she'll want someone who
brings just as much to the table.
Maybe I'm wrong.
I hope so. I'd like her to be happy.
I'm happy, and I want
everyone to be happy.
Are you really happy?
I'm happier than I have ever been.
Happy, impatient, excited.
Don't say too much.
It frightens me.
We've still got months.
Nothing will go wrong.
Bad harvest, bad harvest.
What does that mean?
In the old days, when the crop was good,
the farmers used to shout "Bad harvest!",
so the gods wouldn't grow jealous
of their luck and destroy them.
Bad harvest!
That ought to do it.
Let's hope so.
We'd better hurry or we'll
be late for breakfast.
- Well? - She wants
you. In the drawing room.
What did she say?
What did you say?
I told her your crime was
an excess of loyalty,
that your devotion to
her had made you blind.
It was the smugness of the
doctor that got my goat.
That, I did not say.
No, no. The point is, did it work?
I reminded her how hard it is to
find properly trained staff now.
Yeah. And did it work?
I asked her how long it
had taken to break you in.
We'll have less of that talk.
I just want to know, did it work?
She's going to give you one more chance.
Hallelujah!
But mind you, act surprised
when she tells you.
I will rival Saint Paul
in my astonishment.
Right.
Well, you better get upstairs.
Oh, and Miss Denker,
I don't want to hear another
mention of my unfortunate nephew.
Oh, well, that rather depends.
- On what?
- On whether or not
I need to mention him again.
He's not arrived, then?
No, not yet.
But what we want to know is, by
what power you made him come here.
Well, power of personality.
I'm not sure it would've worked for me.
Works for me. Are you quite well?
I will be all right as long
as no one asks me how I am.
You heard your note nearly
proved fatal to poor Denker?
Well, I only intended that she
be ticked off, not beheaded.
I gather it was Spratt who saved her,
which is a surprise in any number of ways.
Mama, what are you doing?
Carson, Carson, can you change these
place cards in the dining room?
- I'm not sure her ladyship...
- Robert?
- Just do it.
- Yes, very well, m'lord.
You'll be in a very junior seat.
Il faut reculer pour mieux sauter.
I found my editor.
And had some fun, too, I hope.
I went dancing at the Cafe de Paris,
which felt very young and gay.
And we saw Henry Talbot
try out a racing car.
So, now we're all members
of the Bright Young Things.
I don't know about "bright."
The Right Honourable Neville Chamberlain,
Minister for Health.
Lord Grantham. Lady Grantham.
Minister, how kind of you to find
time for us in your busy schedule.
We're very grateful.
I wouldn't have the courage
to refuse your mother-in-law.
There you are.
How is dear Anne?
She sends her greetings.
Oh, how grown up you all are.
You know, I remember so well when
you and she were young and carefree,
looking for fun wherever
you could find it.
I know you do.
Yes, well, but I always say,
let the past stay in the past.
I always say that, too.
Have you met my cousin Mrs Crawley?
No, indeed. It's a great honour.
I gather you're here to discuss the
new plans for managing our health.
I know I'm here to discuss a topic
Lady Grantham is interested in.
Excuse me, would you
care for one of these?
Thank you.
I thought you needed rescuing.
Our own scrapes are bad enough without
being dragged into other people's.
How well you understand me.
I'm afraid you're in for
some rigorous debate.
I wish I weren't.
Shall we go in?
We don't want to wear the minister out
before he's even had a chance to sit down.
She can't protect him in the dining room.
You'll stop at nothing to get
your own way. Isn't that the truth?
Indeed.
It is a quality I share with Marlborough,
Wellington and my late mother.
I was trained in a hard school
and I fight accordingly.
No, he's a coming man. I've read
he may be prime minister one day.
Well, he's no friend of the unions.
For which he is to be congratulated.
Is the consomme ready, Mrs Patmore?
We should get out of your way.
You never said how the trial went.
I didn't have to testify in the end.
He looked at the list of
witnesses and changed his plea.
You must have a sense
of unfinished business.
That's clever of you.
I won't ask what it was, but I
hope you can leave it behind.
I'm not sure. But thank you.
Mr Molesley says the Dowager's
got the bit between her teeth.
Then I don't give much for
Mr Chamberlain's chances.
- Nor me. - But surely, if
it's important to the area,
he'll want to listen?
He'll just want to get out alive.
The system has worked well
here for a hundred years!
Why must we destroy everything in our
path simply for the sake of change?
I'm not sure that's a true
representation of the case.
Exactly. There are many
benefits to be had from the plan.
But benefits for whom?
Goodness.
I thought I was here to be
lectured by a united group,
not to witness a battle royal.
Oh! Don't you enjoy a good fight?
I'm not sure I do, really.
My mother-in-law has a certain myopia when
it comes to anyone else's point of view.
On the contrary, I have
a clarity of vision
that allows me to resist a
housemaid's trap of sentimentality.
Your enthusiasm is getting
the better of your manners.
Can't we stop this beastly row?
How I wish we could.
Because I...
I...
I'm so sorry...
Thomas, on his left side.
Give me napkins!
I'll call the ambulance.
- Keep him warm.
- Take my coat.
- What is it?
- His ulcer has burst.
- What?
- Will he be all right?
We must get him to hospital
as quickly as we can.
I'm here, darling, don't worry.
If this is it, just know I
have loved you very, very much.
This isn't it, darling.
Don't... We won't let this be it.
- Some water?
- No! No water.
Just keep him steady until
the ambulance arrives.
Is he very bad?
I've rung for the ambulance.
It'll be here at any moment.
Miss Baxter, Anna, fetch
their ladyships' coats.
- Don't forget Lady Edith.
- What about me, Mr Carson?
You might put together some
things that could be useful.
But hurry, there's no time to lose.
I can't believe it.
Life is short, death is sure.
That is all we know.
There is a man who's been
shaken to the roots of his soul.
Everything he based his life
on has proved mortal, after all.
We've no time for philosophy, Mrs Patmore.
What can we do to help?
Let's send up some coffee.
Lady Grantham, I'm not sure
how much use I can be here.
Of course, you should go.
I will consider the new plan.
Don't. That is, let it stand.
I believe the change will work
well for both establishments.
Very well.
- Lady Grantham.
- Give my love to dear Annie.
I will.
The ambulance is here!
Don't reprimand me, Mama, I think
the new system will be better
and I haven't got time to be diplomatic.
Don't you think I have
enough things to worry about?
It's better we should be honest.
There've been too many secrets.
Let's have no more of them.
If you mean Marigold, that's
settled and you know I am sorry.
Now let us concentrate on Robert?
They're ready. They want to take him now.
Girls. Mary. Edith.
We must go!
Edith, dear, telephone with any news.
- No matter how late.
- I will.
I'll take you home in my
car. And Lady Grantham.
In a moment.
You're quite pale.
We'll go together.
You've had a shock.
I think I've had a few
shocks this evening.
- They're bringing your car round.
- Oh, let the ambulance get away.
There's a dinner that delivered
more than you bargained for.
Are you going to follow them?
I don't want to crowd him, but
they'll ring when they have news.
Can you let my office know?
Of course.
If you'll do me a favour
and answer one question.
Why did you come here tonight?
Your grandmother-in-law
can be very persuasive.
I'd love to know how she did it.
My wife has a brother
called Horace de Vere Cole.
- You may have heard of him.
- The prankster?
Didn't he board a warship pretending to
be the leader of a Turkish delegation?
Abyssinian, but yes.
He was always doing that sort of thing.
Some years ago, he and a few friends
dug a trench across Piccadilly
and London was thrown into total chaos.
- But what --
- I was one of the chaps responsible.
We dressed as workmen
and no one stopped us.
And by the time we'd finished
every road was jammed
from the East End to Belgrave Square.
And old Lady Grantham
threatened to give you away?
It was long ago now,
but the papers would be sure to
make it look as bad as possible
and a dinner seemed a price
worth paying to avert it.
And there's my car.
So, I'd better be off.
Thank you, m'lady.
That was Lady Mary.
His lordship's had his
operation and now he's resting.
Her ladyship is staying overnight,
but Lady Mary and Lady
Edith will come home.
- What was the operation?
- They performed a gastrectomy.
What's that?
No business of ours.
Will he be all right?
It sounds as if he has a good chance.
Thank God.
I'll find out if there's
anything he needs in the morning.
I'll walk down there now with
some things for her ladyship.
I'll come with you.
I'm quite relieved.
Of course you are.
No, I didn't think I'd mind one
way or the other, to be honest.
I must be getting soft in my old age.
Well, don't let the other animals
find out, or they'll pounce.
Leave him alone. Now, we should go.
We can take it in turns tomorrow.
So Mama can have some rest.
Very well.
I'll go first. Stark can take
me there and bring Mama back.
What a terrifying reminder.
In one second your whole life can change.
Yes.
It only takes a moment for
everything to feel quite different.
I'm going to check on the children.
Of course you are.
Good night.
How is he?
He'll be all right, but it's
knocked the stuffing out of him.
We'll have to make sure the load
is lightened when he comes home.
To be more precise, Tom,
from now on you and I need to take
full responsibility for the estate.
We'll involve him in the
big decisions of course,
but he mustn't have any more worry.
It's why he got the
ulcer in the first place.
So long live our own Queen Mary.
Good night.
Mr Carson told us his
lordship is going to recover.
They seem to think so.
Everyone was very happy to hear it.
Can I fetch you anything?
I just want to go to bed.
- You must be absolutely
exhausted. - Hmm.
Anna, can I ask you something?
Is there any talk in the servants'
hall about Miss Marigold?
What sort of talk, m'lady?
Well, everyone thinks she's a lucky
little girl, being taken in by the family.
But they would think that.
And that's all you want to say?
Why? What else should I say?
Never mind.
I'm too tired to talk any more tonight.
We are opening the house for one day
for charity and there is none to it.
What are they paying to see?
We have nothing to show them.
- Do you need cheering up?
- We all need it sometimes m'lady.
Have you found anyone
to hit with that yet?
If I could choose between principle and
logic, I'd take principle every time!